Guide to the Arnold More Knight Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arnold More Knight papers
1845-1854
MS 1386
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The papers consist of nine journals documenting the military career of Arnold More Knight in India and South Africa. Also included is a volume of Sikh scripture, written in Panjabi, and captured by Knight after the Battle of Aliwal.
Knight, Arnold More
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Tony Zwicker, 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of nine journals documenting the military career of Arnold More Knight from 1845 to 1854 in India and South Africa. The journals contains entries of a personal nature but there are also eye-witness accounts of the Battle of Aliwal in India, Sir Harry Smith's interview with Chief Macomo at Port Elizabeth in South Africa, and the Kaffir War of 1851 to 1852. Also included is a volume of the first part of the Holy Scripture of the Sikhs, written in Panjabi, and captured by Knight at the Battle of Aliwal.
Biographical / Historical
Arnold More Knight purchased his commission in the British army in 1845. As a lieutenant in the 16th Lancers, he was posted to India and served under Sir Harry Smith. At the Battle of Aliwal, Knight captured the Sikh volume which is found in the papers. In 1846 he returned to England.
Knight's two subsequent tours of duty took him to South Africa. In 1847 he commanded Sir Harry Smith's Cavalry Escort. Knight accompanied Smith to Port Elizabeth, King William's town, and Fort Beaufort. After journeying back to England, Knight returned to South Africa in 1851, serving with the Cape Mounted Rifles during the Kaffir War. Following the war, Knight was stationed at the frontier and in Cape Town.
Sikh War, 1845-1846; Sikhism -- Sacred books; South Africa -- History -- Frontier Wars, 1811-1878; Diaries; Soldiers; Knight, Arnold More
- Inventory
  - Journals
    - 1845 Jul to 1846 Apr (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1846 Apr to Jul (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1846 Aug to Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1847 Sep to 1848 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1851 May to Nov (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1851 Nov to 1852 Jul (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1852 Jul to 1853 Feb (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1853 Mar to 1854 Jun (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1854 Jun to Dec (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sikh Scripture, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)